Hi, this is a small little workflow tutorial for Rhino Spatial.
Rhino Spatial is a grasshopper plugin for working with site context directly in Rhino.
We're gonna start with the installation.
The easiest way to install Rhino Spatial is via the package manager.
Make sure to include pre-releases when searching, because right now it's in alpha.
Let's search for Rhino Spatial and there it should be.
Just click on install.
You also can install it via the component folder.
I did pre-load some data sets in this definition, but everything else I'm gonna do from scratch.
The plugin is centered around the spatial context component.
The basic idea behind it is we have a lot of data sets, we want to align to the same
spatial coordinates.
The spatial context component has a few inputs, only one of the inputs is needed and that's
the open map.
We open it via a button.
Other inputs like use absolute coordinates or reference URL are not needed.
By default the Rhino Spatial component loads everything near the zero zero point of Rhino,
Rhino works best around the zero zero point, but you might want to use the absolute coordinates
and for that we have the Boolean toggle here.
Another helpful input is the reference URL.
For example I can choose this WFS layer here as a reference URL and then the map that's
gonna load is pre-loaded around the same area this data set is pre-loaded.
So to select our area now we're just gonna click the button.
Then a browser window is going to open up and here you can see the pre-selected area
and we can select the area.
I am going to select this area around the river.
You can resize afterwards.
Once you've selected the area you can just close the window.
Now we have loaded the spatial context.
If we now want to load the vector data here we're gonna need the load WFS component.
It can load a few different file types, some local, some URL.
As I said you don't really need the reference URL so you can disconnect it right now.
Usually vector data sets have a few layers and for that we have the list layers component.
In this case we want to list the vector layers which is the list WFS layers.
I know that there is just one layer in there which we can see if we add a panel you only
see the one layer.
So we just can connect the layer and the WFS URL.
The last thing we need is just the spatial context component.
And now it did load all the vector data around the area we selected.
Next I want to load in some WMS data.
In our case here it's an aerial image.
For that we need the load WMS component and a list WMS layers component.
I know for a fact that this link has a few layers in there so we can look at them via
the panel.
We want to select layer 5 or rather layer 6 here.
We are going to do this via the list item component and a number slider.
We can now connect the layer.
You can only ever load one WMS layer.
For the vector layers you can load as many as you want via just one component.
Then we need to connect the URL.
And of course the most important the spatial context component.
And there we have an aerial image aligned to the vector data.
Next I want to load some GeoTIFF files.
For that I am going to disable the aerial image here.
The GeoTIFF component up here expects a local GeoTIFF file.
It's pretty easy.
Just connect the local file via a file path component.
And of course we need our spatial context again.
And there we have it loaded in.
One thing of course is that it only loads georeferenced GeoTIFF files.
If it can't read the EPSG data we can't really put it in the right spatial context.
Next I want to load some terrain data.
For that we need the load terrain component.
Load terrain of course needs the spatial context.
The load terrain component has some fallback data.
As you can see it's not that fine but it also accepts a few data sources.
For example WCS URLs, local DEM files and a few more just basic point clouds.
You can always read up in the github what it can load.
And I did prepare this URL here which should be a bit better data.
There we go.
Next I want to load in some LOD2 data.
There we have a few options again.
We have the WFS or LOD links.
We can load in some CTGML or CTJSON data.
In general most LOD2 data in an ACIP folder can be loaded in.
For loading in the LOD2 data we need the LOD2 component.
We need the source data.
We can select a layer here but we don't need to.
And of course we need the spatial context.
This might load a bit.
And there we have it.
The LOD2 data is loaded in.
It took a fairly long time to load in.
And now we can work with it of course.
For example we can bake it.
Next is something a bit different.
We gonna load in some OpenStreetMap data via the LoadOSM component.
The OSM component loads in OpenStreetMap data via the Overpass API.
So the only thing you really need is the spatial context component.
Also you need to select what things you wanna load in via a boolean toggle.
I wanna load in all the data so I'm gonna select true and just select all of the things.
And now we just need to connect the spatial context component.
Here again this might load a fairly long time.
Ok that took a long time but now it's loaded in.
I'm gonna hide the LOD2 data for a second here.
By the way by default buildings are always loaded in.
You just need to select the other ones.
I'm gonna display it a bit better.
And there we have it displayed a bit better.
Now one thing you see here is that the spatial context component aligns everything or rather
every 3D element in 3D space.
So the LOD2 data usually sits at the same height as the OSM data.
But all the 2D data which includes in this case the greenery or water is displayed in
one plane.
So if we load in the terrain data we should see that the OSM buildings are aligned to
the terrain fairly well.
And yeah we can see it here.
Oh and the buildings not looking right here are just mesh rendering alias.
So if you bake the buildings they should be displayed right because the data is right.
It's just a display failure here.
I think the mesh count is too low.
And now as a bit of a bonus here is the last component.
It's the Google 3D tiles component.
It's under a new tab because it's under the view tab.
It doesn't allow you to actually download the data you just can display the data.
And that's what we are doing here.
We are basically aligning a Google Maps or Google Earth rather image to our spatial context.
What we need for that is a Google API key or rather a Maps tiles API key.
As I said you only can use the data for display purposes.
So Google doesn't allow you to save it.
I've loaded my API key in here.
We of course want it in the same spatial context so we are going to load the spatial context.
By default it is disabled because it takes a fairly long time to load.
To enable it you just need a boolean toggle again.
There it is loaded in.
As you can see it is a bit buggy.
Sometimes you need to reselect the spatial context because right now it only loads half.
I clearly need to work a bit more on it.
Let me turn off the preview here.
You can see it's not a lot selected here.
You can try to rerun it or usually it just helps to reselect the area.
And by the way baking doesn't really work.
You can click on it but it doesn't bake anything.
Because as I've mentioned you are not really allowed to save the data.
You can only display it and look at it in the context in this case.
You might want to see if something you have modeled is aligned to it or rather what it
would look like behind the things you have modeled.
And that's basically all the functionality.